Okay,
good morning. Today's דף daf is דף ה', Daf Hey,
and
we will be making reference to פסוקים, pesukim,
specifically פרשת בא Parshat Bo in פרק י"ב Perek Yud-Bet starting from
פסוק ט"ו, Pasuk Tet-Vav, and then we'll also make a passing reference
to דברים Devarim in פרשת ראה. Parshat Re'eh.
Yesterday we were talking about how you know the זמן, zman, just
to get us in contact, how you know that you do the
השבתה, hashbata, you know, when basically when it kicks in, you do
the ביעור biur in the middle of the day before, like at
ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, right? So why isn't it right before, like
the night before? We said, well, that can't be
because everything is sort of connected, getting rid of שאור se'or to
eating חמץ, chametz, and that to מצה, matzah, and then we know
that when you eat מצה, matzah, you can't have חמץ chametz already,
so you have to have gotten rid of it beforehand. So we
said, all right, fine, well, maybe well beforehand, maybe maybe even a
whole full night before, twenty-four hours before? We said, no, you don't
do that because it says doing it in the day. Okay, so
why not first thing in the morning? זריזין מקדימין? zerizin makdimin? So
we said, well, because it says אך. ach. אך ach is מחלק,
mechaleq, that you do, you know, sort of half of the day.
So or something like that. But basically we use all
that, all these different parts of the פסוקים pesukim to teach you
that that's basically when you do it, we do it after six
hours in the day. Okay, אמר דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, amar d'bei
Rabbi Ishmael tana, so we're about one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven,
eight, nine or so lines
down
on ה' עמוד א', Hey amud aleph, and דבי d'bei is where
we are, the last word on that line is דבי. d'bei.
You
see that?
Yep. Okay. דבי
רבי
ישמעאל תנא מצינו י"ד שנקרא ראשון.
D'bei
Rabbi
Ishmael tana matzinu yud-daled shenikra rishon. So how do, this is a
slightly different answer, so how do we know that you have to
get rid of it on the fourteenth? Because there's an explicit פסוק
pasuk saying that the fourteenth is actually called ראשון. rishon. שנאמר בראשון
בארבעה עשר יום
לחודש.
Shene'emar barishon b'arba'ah asar
yom lachodesh. So that's also called ראשון. rishon. So when we say
אך ביום הראשון תשביתו שאור מבתיכם, ach bayom harishon tashbitu se'or mibateichem,
the first day doesn't mean the first day of פסח, Pesach, but
rather means the day beforehand, the fourteenth of ניסן, Nisan, which is
also called
ראשון, rishon, right? It's in that פסוק: pasuk: שבעת ימים מצות תאכלו
אך ביום הראשון תשביתו שאור מבתיכם shivat yamim matzot tochelu ach bayom
harishon tashbitu se'or mibateichem and then that's one time when, you know,
where we talk about יום הראשון, yom harishon, and then here's another
time where we have it later, a few פסוקים pesukim later, if
you're looking in your חומש, chumash, I'll just read the: כי כל
אוכל חמץ ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מיום הראשון עד יום השביעי, ki kol
ochel chametz venichreta hanefesh hahi miyom harishon ad yom hashvi'i, if you
eat חמץ chametz in these days, from the first day of the
חג chag until the last day of the חג. chag. And then
it says וביום הראשון מקרא קודש וביום השביעי מקרא קודש יהיה לכם.
ubayom harishon mikra kodesh vubayom hashvi'i mikra kodesh yihyeh lachem. And then
go one פסוק pasuk further, פסוק י"ח: pasuk yud-chet: בראשון בארבעה עשר
יום לחודש בערב תאכלו מצות. barishon b'arba'ah asar yom lachodesh baerev tochlu
matzot. So בראשון barishon is called בארבעה עשר יום לחודש, b'arba'ah asar
yom lachodesh, right? You see that?
Well, clearly in that פסוק, pasuk, ראשון rishon doesn't mean that.
Well, ראשון rishon
in that פסוק pasuk means the first month of the year. Oh,
interesting.
בראשון, barishon,
in the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, it
says. That's clearly the פשט. pshat.
Yeah, true.
I mean, it's no big deal, so it's a דרש, drash, a
hermeneutic. Right, okay, yeah.
רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר ראשון דמעיקרא
משמע, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar
rishon d'meikara
mashma, so he's saying, forget that, ראשון rishon means, when you see
the
word ראשון, rishon, it really means the day before, like beforehand. ראשון
rishon means before. It doesn't only mean first, although we say יום
ראשון yom rishon is the first day of the week, but you
know, at least in biblical context, when you see that word, it
could also mean beforehand because there is a פסוק pasuk that tells
you as much,
although this is not a תורה Torah פסוק, pasuk, but nevertheless, we're
saying the same principle would apply. And that is דאמר קרא
הראשון אדם תולד,
damar kra
harishon adam tivaled,
so were you born prior to, like, the first man?
So that would mean that ראשון rishon means prior. So when we
see this ראשון, rishon, it means the day prior to the חג.
chag. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't really like this. So you're saying
every time you see ראשון rishon it means prior? What do you
do with other פסוקים pesukim that clearly do not indicate such? Like
אלא מעתה ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון, ella me'ata ul'kachtem lachem bayom harishon,
לולב, lulav, right? Take the first day of the
חג, chag, פרי עץ הדר כפת תמרים. pri etz hadar kapot temarim.
Take we all take our לולב Lulav the first day of סוכות
Sukkot we're doing it all wrong we really need to take it
the day before the first day of סוכות? Sukkot? That's when we're
taking our לולב? Lulav? What do you do with that? ראשון rishon
can't mean before. So הכא נמי מכאן רישא? hacha nami mika'an reisha?
Would we be saying that? Surely we don't say that. So the
גמרא Gemara says שאני התם דכתיב shani hatam d'chtiv ושמחתם לפני ה'
אלקיכם שבעת ימים u'semachtem lifnei Hashem Elokeichem shivat yamim as I mentioned.
And the פסוק pasuk is that you should rejoice in front of
Hashem for seven days.
But then we're sort of comparing it: מה שביעי שביעי לחג, ma
shevii shevii lachag, just like the seventh day that you're rejoicing clearly
means the seventh day of the חג, chag, אף ראשון ראשון לחג.
af rishon rishon lachag. So too the first day is the first
day of the חג. chag. So then so what? How does that
help you? Because then you say that you should still be saying
the same thing here? הכא נמי כתיב אך ביום הראשון תשביתו. hacha
nami ktiv ach bayom harishon tashbitu. That was that same פסוק pasuk
that I was reading here. Then
again שבעת ימים, shivat yamim, that's פסוק pasuk ט"ו tet vav in
בא. Bo. שבעת ימים מצות תאכלו אך ביום הראשון תשביתו שאור מבתיכם.
shivat yamim matzot
tochelu ach bayom harishon tashbitu se'or mibateichem. So seven days are clearly
the seven days of eating מצה matzah is the seven days of
the חג. chag. So then according to what you just said by
applying the rules from סוכות Sukkot to פסח, Pesach, that would mean
ביום הראשון bayom harishon means you get rid of it on the
first day of פסח, Pesach, and we were just saying that you
don't get rid of it the first day of פסח, Pesach, you
get rid of it the day before.
So הכא נמי אך יום ראשון שבעת ימים מצות
תאכלו.
hacha nami ach yom
rishon shivat yamim matzot tochelu. So
then the גמרא Gemara says, well okay, אם כן נכתוב קרא ראשון.
im ken nictov kra rishon. It
could have said אך ביום ראשון תשביתו שאור מבתיכם. ach bayom rishon
tashbitu se'or mibateichem. But what does it say? It says אך ביום
הראשון. ach bayom harishon.
So הראשון למה לי? harishon lama li? שמע מינה לכדאמרן shma mina
lechde'amran because of the extra ה, heh, it's what we say before
that it doesn't mean the first day of the חג, chag, rather
it means the day before. And that's what he's saying that ראשון
rishon means the day before. So what? אי הכי התם הראשון
למה לי? ei hachi hatam harishon lama li?
So we still have הראשון harishon in סוכות. Sukkot. No different, right?
If you're saying the ה heh means the day before, then we
have the same ה heh by סוכות. Sukkot. Again, ולקחתם לכם ביום
הראשון. u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon.
So if you're trying to say that הראשון harishon means the day
before, then in סוכות Sukkot it should also mean the day before,
but again no one's taking their לולב Lulav and אתרוג Esrog the
day before סוכות Sukkot begins. And
also ותו התם כתיב ביום הראשון שבתון וביום השמיני שבתון.
u'tu hatam ktiv bayom harishon shabaton
uvayom hashmini shabaton. אימא ראשון דמעיקרא משמע? eima rishon demeikara mashma? So
say the same thing, just like it
says ביום הראשון שבתון וביום השמיני שבתון bayom harishon shabaton uvayom hashmini
shabaton which is referring to שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret.
So are you gonna say over there that the ראשון rishon means
the day before? Like forget about taking לולב Lulav for a second,
right? ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון. u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon. What about the
actual days of the חג? chag? You know the מועדים, moadim,
where you're not allowed to do work? It says over there ביום
הראשון שבתון וביום השמיני שבתון. bayom harishon shabaton uvayom hashmini shabaton. So
now we're saying it doesn't mean the first day of the חג
chag and it means the day before the first day of the
חג? chag? Clearly no one's saying that.
So okay, we say שאני התם דאמר קרא ביום השמיני שבתון. shani
hatam de'amar kra bayom hashmini shabaton. Oh no, because there it mentions
the first day and the last day of the חג. chag. So
certainly by סוכות Sukkot מה שמיני שמיני דחג
אף ראשון ראשון לחג.
ma shemini shemini
d'chag af rishon rishon lachag. So certainly no, it doesn't mean a
day before the first day of the חג, chag, because the eighth
day doesn't mean anything other than the eighth day. So then just
like the eighth day is a חג, chag, the first day is
a חג, chag, unlike over here where it doesn't say that.
You just say אך ביום הראשון תשביתו שאור מבתיכם. ach bayom harishon
tashbitu se'or mibateichem.
But nevertheless the problem is ביום הראשון מקרא קודש וביום השביעי מקרא
קודש יהיה לכם כל מלאכה לא יעשה בהם. bayom harishon mikra kodesh
uvayom hashvii mikra kodesh yihiyeh lachem kol melacha lo ye'aseh bahem. Right?
So basically if you look at all the פסוקים psukim we could
have said the same thing, just like the seventh day is a
מקרא קודש mikra kodesh and certainly the first day is a מקרא
קודש. mikra kodesh. And then if we're saying that first day is
ביום הראשון bayom harishon and that's the day you get rid of
it, you know then we're having problems, right? Clearly the first day
doesn't mean the day before. See that? I mean because the פסוקים
psukim are so parallel, like it's hard to get out of it.
And it's a bit of a stretch to try and call it
the day before, they're really trying this.
Well then you'll see where the גמרא Gemara goes with it, and
remember there were other דרשות drashot we already had.
So are you gonna say that here too?
אף ראשון ראשון לחג. af rishon rishon lachag. So then הראשון למה
לי? harishon lama li? So okay fine, if we're saying that by
comparing
it to the eighth day that it really means the day of
the חג, chag, then what do we need all this for? למיעוטי
חולו של מועד. lemiyutei cholo shel moed.
So what do you mean? To tell you not
to exclude חול המועד, chol hamoed, meaning to say that that's like
not יום טוב Yom Tov or something like that. know, that you
don't have to cease work in every one of those days.
So our לולב, lulav, right? But
because really
לולב lulav
is only the first day, you know, outside of the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash.
Anyway, so but the point being though, so the ה, ha, we're
saying that you're not allowed to do מלאכה melacha only on the
ימי, yemei, on the ימי yemei like, you know, יום טוב, Yom
Tov, not on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. That's what that's teaching you
to not do. That's the ה הראשון. ha-rishon. What do you mean?
We know that from the פסוק pasuk itself. חול המועד Chol HaMoed
ראשון ושמיני נפקא. rishon u'shemini nafka. It says the first day is
a שבתון Shabbaton and the eighth day is a שבתון, Shabbaton, which
means anything else is not a שבתון. Shabbaton.
So no, איצטריך סלקא דעתך אמינא, itzrich salka deitacha amina, actually not
so fast. We still need
this extra ה hey to teach you that it's really
excluding
חול המועד Chol HaMoed because it says הואיל דכתב רחמנא וביום השמיני.
ho'il dechtav rachmana u'vayom hashmini.
And then we sometimes have this rule, or often have this rule,
ו מוסיף על עניין ראשון. vav mosif al inyan rishon. It says
"and on the eighth day," which means oh okay, and on the
eighth day, maybe the days before too, just since it's saying "and".
"And" is joining it to the days before. ו מוסיף על עניין
ראשון vav mosif al inyan rishon דאפילו בחול המועד d'afilo b'chol ha'moed
צריכא
לאשמעינן. tzerich le'ashme'inan.
No, doesn't mean eighth including the intermediate days in between, rather it
means eighth adding on to the first, right? Just like the first
day was a שבתון, Shabbaton, so too the eighth day is a
שבתון. Shabbaton. So the reason why you have to do that is
because
you have to do וביום השמיני, u'vayom hashmini, so therefore coming to
teach you the ה hey from beforehand that it's no, just the
first and the eighth, nothing in between, right? That's what's constructed so
far. It says since it says וביום השמיני, u'vayom hashmini, you would
have thought that anything beforehand
is included in the איסור עשיית מלאכה. issur asiyat melacha. Comes to
teach you וביום הראשון, u'vayom harishon, right? הראשון harishon is
saying, you know, just just the first day and not the ימי
חול המועד. yemei Chol HaMoed. Then the גמרא Gemara says I don't
get it. If the whole reason why we have to have the
ו u is because, you know, is the ה, hey, right? Because
of the ו, u, right? וביום השמיני, u'vayom hashmini, therefore you have
to have הראשון. harishon. Then then just forget the ו, vav, then
you wouldn't need the ה hey beforehand, right? Don't say וביום השמיני.
u'vayom hashmini. Say it differently, say ביום ראשון שבתון ביום שמיני שבתון,
beyom rishon Shabbaton beyom shemini Shabbaton, right?
Instead of saying וביום השמיני, u'vayom hashmini, which then necessitates you saying
הראשון harishon to exclude חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, don't have either. Keep
it simple, right? What do we having all these extra letters and
words for? ומתורץ התם דכתיב ביום הראשון מקרא קודש u'mtu hatam d'chtiv
beyom harishon mikra kodesh שדידכי ראשון דמעיקרא משמע. shede'achay rishon demikara mashma.
Right. What do you do about that? ביום הראשון מקרא
קודש beyom harishon mikra kodesh as I was saying before, at some
point you can't get out of it, right? You say the first
day is a מקרא קודש mikra kodesh and it says ביום הראשון
מקרא קודש. beyom harishon mikra kodesh. Doesn't say ביום ראשון. beyom rishon.
We're saying הראשון, harishon, right? ביום הראשון מקרא קודש beyom harishon mikra
kodesh if we're just trying to say that that means the day
before, then you know, what do you do about that? We said,
you know, we talked about לולב lulav and all and all that,
and we talked about and we
talked about about all these different things, איסור עשיית מלאכה, issur asiyat
melacha, but at some point basically is what I was saying, that
the parallels get so close that you can't really say that ראשון
rishon means the day before. Right? I mean that's you kind of
see that.
I
don't need to belabor the point. So we say okay fine, so
the parallels are too convincing.
But so then what we're saying is that we either then,
interestingly enough, we're going to keep our לימוד limmud that ראשון rishon
really means the day before, but what do you do about all
these other proofs that clearly indicate otherwise? So that's for a דרש.
drash. אלא הני שלושה ראשון מיבעי ליה כדתני דבי רבי ישמעאל דתני
דבי רבי ישמעאל. Ella hanei shelosha rishon miba'ei lei k'tanya devei Rabbi
Yishmael d'tanya devei Rabbi Yishmael. בפסח... be-Pesach...
At this moment I'm sorry.
No, the גמרא Gemara will explain it.
But at this moment they're most satisfied with it meaning the day
before.
Like in, like in, well at this at this very second, you
know, before we said אלא, ella, before we just said שלושה אלא
הני שלושה ראשון מיבעי, shelosha ella hanei shelosha rishon miba'ei, we're throwing
it out. Right? You can't. I mean "before," because then that means
you're, you know, not doing מלאכה melacha the day before סוכות, Succos,
right? Or whatever it is, you know.
We're taking לולב lulav on totally other days, not doing מלאכה melacha
on totally other days, and you know, so it can't mean that.
Just like, in other words, so you know,
then we would not be doing מלאכה, melacha, the, you know, on
the day before the first day of פסח, Pesach, right? Because it
says, you know,
ביום הראשון מקרא קודש, beyom harishon mikra kodesh, doesn't
say ביום ראשון. beyom rishon. We're saying הראשון, harishon, right? So then
the גמרא Gemara says no, actually, this answer right right here is
אלא הני, ella hanei, really ראשון rishon does mean the day before.
So what do you do with all these הראשוןs harishon that we
had? But ביום הראשון מקרא קודש Bayom harishon mikra kodesh is not.
It’s telling you it’s the first day of the חג. chag. So
now how are you getting that? Why are you saying one ראשון
rishon means the day before versus the other days, right, which don’t
mean the day before, really means the first day of the חג?
chag? So what we’re saying is אלא הני שלושה ראשון יבעי ליה
כדתני דבי רבי ישמעאל. Ela hanei shelosha rishon yibaei lei kedatanya devei
Rabbi Yishmael. That’s that’s used for like דרוש drush purposes.
So basically
we’re saying בשכר שלושה ראשון Bisechar shelosha rishon for the
because of the these if you will ראשון's rishon's that are that
are that are mentioned
in these contexts, like let’s say פסח, Pesach, סוכות, Succot, and the
לולב, Lulav, you know, איסור מלאכה issur melachah on סוכות Succot and
then the מצוה mitzvah to take a לולב Lulav on... איסור מלאכה
issur melachah
which applies both to פסח Pesach and both to סוכות Succot which
are mentioned in הראשון, harishon, you know, with the ראשון rishon and
also לולב Lulav which is mentioned by a
ראשון. rishon. For all these different ראשון's rishon's and the גמרא Gemara
will explain it, then
the
merit of these things that we do in these firsts, we sort
of we obviate the other first. What do we mean by that?
דתני דבי רבי ישמעאל בשכר שלושה ראשון זכו לשלושה ראשון.
Detanya devei Rabbi Yishmael bisechar shelosha
rishon zachu leshelosha rishon. So in
because of the these ראשון rishon we we get another ראשון. rishon.
What do we mean by that? להכרית זרעו של עשו. Lehachrit zaro
shel Esav. The three ראשון rishon we get reward for are להכרית
זרעו של עשו lehachrit zaro shel Esav and בניין בית המקדש binyan
Beit HaMikdash and לשמו של משיח. lishmo shel Mashiach. זרעו של עשו
Zaro shel Esav
דכתיב dechtiv ויצא הראשון אדמוני כולו כאדרת שיער.
Vayeitzei harishon admoni
kulo keaderet se'ar. So because of one הראשון harishon that we do
and actually the מהרש"א Maharsha explains it, let me just get the
open up the מהרש"א. Maharsha. That’s serious pamphlet. Yeah
it is.
Yeah this is more than pamphlet, this is like a wild thing.
Yeah
let
me just read it over here. I'll read in the מהרש"א Maharsha
first actually. So he says listen, where are ראשון's rishon's mentioned? The
ראשון's rishon's are mentioned in פסח, Pesach, right? Clearly. And in פסח
Pesach
what is it? פסח Pesach is a celebration of the גאולה geulah
from מצרים, Mitzrayim, right? So the גאולה geulah from מצרים Mitzrayim we
were redeemed. So too
that we have that להכרית זרעו של עשו. lehachrit zaro shel Esav.
So who’s
and בניין בית המקדש binyan Beit HaMikdash and לשמו של משיח. lishmo
shel Mashiach. Those are the three things. So just like in פסח
Pesach God redeemed us and that’s what we’re celebrating and then you
know and there and with that we have clearly the עשר
מכות. eser
makot.
Then so too because of this because of this שביתה shvitah on
this on this first day, we’ll also be merited to be redeemed
in the future and עשו Esav is from עשו Esav who’s now
the one subjugating us, right? So just like we had a prior
גאולה, geulah, so so too we will have a future גאולה geulah
from the זרעו של עשו, zaro shel Esav, you know, very appropriate
I guess to today which is שבעה עשר
בתמוז.
Shiva
Asar B'Tammuz. And you know so God will we will merit that
that God will redeem us from our enemies. So you
know he also mentions that you know that he gets a little
homiletic that the that the דרש drash that we all kind of
know that the שאור se'or is right representing the יצר הרע. yetzer
hara. So if you can manage to overcome that, which is the
כוח koach of עשו Esav which represents everything evil, then we will
you know
עתיד לבוא atid lavo we will not have this desire to do
evil. So anyway, so that’s one. And then we have another שביתה
shvitah in חג הסוכות. Chag HaSuccot. Also says בראשון. barishon. So the
same thing more or less, that’s also commemorating the redemption from מצרים.
Mitzrayim. כי בסוכות הושבתי את בני ישראל בהוציאי אותם מארץ מצרים. Ki
vasuccot hoshavti et b'nei Yisrael behotzi'i otam me'eretz Mitzrayim. I’m reading it
from the מהרש"א Maharsha still.
And that represents the you know another building in the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. So the first one is the first one is the
גאולה, geulah, right, that פסח Pesach is, it represents pure גאולה, geulah,
and that will then represent us being redeemed from עשו. Esav. And
then the other one is בסוכות הושבתי את בני ישראל בהוציאי אותם
מארץ מצרים,
Besuccot hoshavti et b'nei Yisrael
behotzi'i otam me'eretz Mitzrayim, that also represents the you know another basically
redemption which is and the building in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
And then God will be משרה השכינה mashre hashchinah just like God
was פורס סוכת שלום pores sukkat shalom on us which were the
ענני הכבוד, ananei hakavod, right? So that’s
that’s another one. And then by לולב, Lulav, ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון.
Ulekachtem lachem bayom harishon. So that’s a day full of שמחה. simcha.
סוכות Succot is זמן שמחתנו zman simchatenu basically.
And because of that we will be merited the name of the
משיח Mashiach who is also called a ראשון rishon and According to
the מהרש"א *Maharsha*. So anyways, for these ראשונים *Rishonim* we get these
things. And I'll
just read it in: וחבישה ראשו
של עשו דכתיב ויצא הראשון
אדמוני כלו כאדרת שער *Vachavisha rosho shel Esav dechtiv vayetze harishon admoni
kulo keaderet sear*.
So that's one ראשון rishon *Rishon*. ובניין בית המקדש דכתיב כסא כבוד
מרום מראשון מקום מקדשנו *Uvinyan Beit Hamikdash dechtiv kissei kavod marom merishon
mekom mikdashenu*. So that's a tie-in that the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*
is called a ראשון *Rishon*. I'll just translate that. It says כסא
מרום *Kissei marom*, so
God's
chair of honor or glory, מרום *Marom* is exalted, מראשון *Merishon* from
the very first, from the very beginning, מקום מקדשנו *Mekom mikdashenu* is
a place just like that, that's the place of our בית המקדש
*Beit Hamikdash*. ובשמו של משיח דכתיב ראשון לציון הנה הינם *Uvishemo shel
Mashiach dechtiv rishon leTziyon hinei hinam*. The first of ציון *Tziyon*, they
are here. So
anyway the point being that we didn't really need all these ראשונים
*Rishonim* to, over there, basically what we're saying is he would have
been stuck with all these הראשון *HaRishon*, הראשון *HaRishon*, הראשון *HaRishon* were
it not that we need it for a דרשה *Drasha* purpose, right?
So this one we don't need for a דרשה *Drasha* purpose, so
this is telling you the day before. That's basically what we're saying
right now. It's not the most convincing of פשטים *Pshatim*, at least
not to me.
But again, don't forget this is one of many answers, right?
A very good answer was that you can't get rid of it
after, ליל הסדר *Leil HaSeder* because you already, we have all these
היקשים heikeshim *Hekkeshim*, right? And we're going to get back to that
answer. Or,
so that's, and then that's how I started the day with, oh
you can't do it the day before, what about well before? No,
it says on the day. Why half a day? Because אך ach,
*Ach*, אך ach. *Ach* is חלק *Chelek*, חלק *Chalak*. So that's an
answer we had as well before.
So another answer: רבא אמר מהכא *Rava amar mehacha*. Again, we're still
trying to figure out how we know that we're getting rid of
חמץ chametz. *Chametz* the day before. That's our topic right now for
this דף daf. *Daf*. רבא אמר מהכא *Rava amar mehacha*: לא תשחט
על חמץ chametz דם זבחי *Lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi*, לא
תשחט את הפסח *Lo tishchat et haPesach* ועדיין חמץ chametz קיים *ve'adayin
chametz kayam*. Do not שחטת *Shachatat* on חמץ chametz *Chametz*, literally on
חמץ chametz *Chametz*, but meaning really, don't slaughter it while you still
have חמץ chametz, *Chametz*, right? While you still have it. So you
can't שחט *Shechat* the פסח Pesach *Pesach* and still have חמץ chametz.
*Chametz*. And when is the פסח Pesach, *Pesach* שחטed *Shechted*? שחיטת הפסח
*Shechitat
haPesach* is שחטed *Shechted* basically midday, right? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, trying to take it very literally, ואין הכל בבת אחת כששוחטין
*V'ein hakol bevat achat k'sheshochtin*.
So if it really means don't you, it's meaning each person. Each
person cannot be שחטing *Shechting* at the same time. Right, so if
I'm at
ten o'clock, you'll be ten-twenty, ten-thirty. Right.
If the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* is saying every time you, when you
שחט *Shechat*, you can't have חמץ chametz *Chametz*, okay, so then let's,
that ranges. It begins at the sixth hour. You can't do it,
ten-twenty would be too early because you can't שחט *Shechat* the פסח
Pesach. *Pesach* until midday earliest, but it can go until later, and
it does go until later. You know, and we have this teaching
that the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael. *Bnei Yisrael* go into three כתים
*Katim*, right? That there are three shifts in the בית המקדש *Beit
Hamikdash*. Three shifts. So if I'm in the third shift and I
can wait a little longer, right? So why are we saying
that it all begins at midday?
Yeah, I can be eating my nice roll over there while it's
פסח Pesach, *Pesach* for you, it's sort of like שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*.
If I bring it in early, I bring it in early, so
I'm אסור *Asur* for מלאכה melacha. *Melacha* for me, but you're bringing
it in on time in the summer, right?
So you can do מלאכה melacha *Melacha* later. So too, I'm שחטing
*Shechting* my פסח Pesach, *Pesach* a little bit later, I'm doing it
בזמן *Bizman*, right? You're doing it early. So you can't eat חמץ
chametz *Chametz* and I can? We don't say that. We say it
kicks in for everybody at the same time. So anyway the question
was ואין הכל בבת אחת כששוחטין *V'ein hakol bevat achat k'sheshochtin* would
be the time that it's אסור *Asur* for him. So why don't
we say that? No, because זמן שחיטה אמר רחמנא *Zman shechita amar
Rachmana*. לא תשחט על חמץ chametz, דם זבחי *Lo tishchat al chametz
dam zivchi*. We don't mean literally that it's literally the moment you
do it, but it's the moment that people are doing it and
when it begins for people to do it really. As opposed to
שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*, no individual זמנים *Zmanim*. But it is kind of
a compelling argument for a moment there. אמר רחמנא *Amar Rachmana*. Anyway
so that's what he says. So forget all this היקש heikesh *Hekkesh*,
this היקש hekesh. *Hekkesh* to that. Forget about ראשון *Rishon*, הראשון *HaRishon*,
and he's saying no, take another פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* that's saying you
can't שחט *Shechat* at the time of שחטing *Shechting* of a פסח
Pesach, *Pesach* is what they're basically saying, cannot be
at a time that you have חמץ chametz *Chametz*. And we know
when you שחט *Shechat* the פסח Pesach? *Pesach*, which is the day
before from midday, so from then on you can't have חמץ chametz,
*Chametz*. תניא נמי הכי אך ביום הראשון תשביתו שאור מבתיכם ach bayom
harishon tashbitu se'or mibateichem. *Tanya nami hachi ach bayom harishon tashbitu se'or
mibateichem*. Is it מערב יום טוב me'erev yom tov. *Me'erev Yom Tov*
I get rid of it? Is it the day before? או אינו
אלא ביום טוב O eino ela beyom tov. עצמו *O
eino ela beyom tov atzmo*. Maybe it really means on that day
itself, the first day of פסח *Pesach*. No, we can't say that.
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar *Talmud lomar* לא תשחט *Lo tishchat*. Okay, so
that's yet another answer. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. אומר is yet another
answer for
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva אינו צריך הרי הוא אומר אך ביום הראשון
תשביתו שאור מבתיכם, Eino tzarich harei hu omer ach bayom harishon tashbitu
se'or mibateichem, which is basically
on the first day you have to get rid of שאור se'or
from your households. וכתיב כל מלאכה לא תעשו. Uchtiv kol melacha lo
ta'asu. And it also says מלאכה לא תעשו, melacha lo ta'asu, right?
Oh, but that's a problem. If you take it literally that you
have to get rid of it on the first day, and if
the גמרא Gemara is going to flesh this out, and if you're
going to be burning it, because that's the way you're getting rid
of it, but wait, how can you be doing burning? Burning is
a מלאכה. melacha And it says ביום הראשון, bayom harishon, you can't
be doing מלאכה melacha on the first day.
What if you let the fire be burning? That's interesting, but the
only prohibition is starting a fire.
Well, but the question is aren't we allowed to use fire on
פסח to begin with or on יום טוב, yom tov, right?
That's an even bigger question.
Okay, but you can't benefit from חמץ. chametz. Right, but we'll get
to that, we'll get to this in a minute what רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva must be holding. Anyway, the point being though, his point
is that we can't take ראשון literally in terms of getting rid
of שאור se'or because what he's saying, you know, because if you
know that you can't do מלאכה melacha. on the first day and
then getting rid of חמץ chametz. involves a מלאכה melacha of burning,
it must mean that you do it before. That's his teaching. Again,
if you don't like it, there are other ones. רבי יוסי אומר
אינו צריך. Rabbi Yossi omer eino tzarich.
He's going to basically go back to what we said earlier in
the beginning yesterday, you know, beginning today. הרי הוא אומר אך ביום
הראשון תשביתו שאור מבתיכם.
Harei hu omer ach bayom harishon tashbitu
se'or mibateichem. In the
first
day you've got to get rid of שאור. se'or. That's מערב יום
טוב. yom tov It doesn't mean the first day, it means beforehand.
או אינו אלא ביום טוב. Is
it well it says ביום הראשון, bayom harishon, what does it mean?
Does it mean the day before, does it mean that day? תלמוד
לומר אך חלק, Talmud lomar ach chalak, which we had before, like
you know it's a
this אך, אך ביום הראשון ach bayom harishon divides it. ואי ביום
טוב עצמו מי שרי. Ve'i beyom tov atzmo mi sharei. And what
do you mean? You know and if it's the first day of
פסח, you can't have חמץ chametz at all on the first day
of פסח. So it must mean a day that you can have
חמץ chametz for part of that day and that would be ערב
פסח, erev Pesach, which is sort of like what we said before
with all these היקשים heikeshim, and then we ended up getting to
the אך. So same idea, he just doesn't have all the היקשים,
heikeshim but gets to the same point. ואי ביום טוב
ראשון מי שרי. Ve'i beyom tov rishon mi sharei. And then he
says איתקש השבתת שאור לאכילת חמץ וכל חמץ לאכילת מצה, Itkash hashbatat
se'or la'achilat chametz vechol chametz la'achilat matzah, which is exactly what we
said before. So now you know so
on top we fleshed it out, we said what the היקש was,
but now he basically is going back to the same answer. So
it turns out he does have all these היקשים
and that's what he says.
The prohibition of eating מצה matzah on the 14th of ניסן Nissan
is rabbinic.
The prohibition of oh meaning like why we don't eat מצה matzah
yet because to do it לתיאבון. lete'avon.
Yes, exactly.
Meaning
that in other words, although we can't eat חמץ chametz on the
14th after a certain point, we also have the מנהג minhag of
not eating מצה matzah that day. So Charlie's saying why do we
do that? And the point is that's more of a rabbinic kind
of thing because you want to eat the
מצה matzah like you
know and be really
excited to you know have this מצה. matzah.
Like get this excitement about מצה. matzah.
Some people
extend it
to 30 days that people don't eat מצה matzah for 30 days.
That's a lot. Yeah. Okay, but anyway so the point being though,
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva point was that it can't be on the
first day of יום טוב Yom Tov because it involves a מלאכה.
melacha. So we can learn from there.
אמר רבא. Amar Rava.
Now we turn the page. שמע מינה מדברי רבי עקיבא תלת. Shema
mina midivrei Rabbi Akiva telat. Now we're on ה עמוד ב. Heh
amud bet. We can learn from רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva three things.
And as our Rosh Yeshiva points out, we always learn it's always
these things are coming in packages of three, but we actually really
do learn three things here. שמע מינה תלת. Shema mina telat. These
three things. What do we learn? שמע מינה אין ביעור חמץ אלא
שריפה, Shema mina ein bi'ur chametz ela sereifah, because from רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva? saying it's a מלאכה melacha, problem, right, that means ביעור
bi'ur is שריפה. sereifah. Because again, like there are a number of
ways you could have said שריפה, sereifah, you know, get rid of
your חמץ, chametz right? Doesn't say... how do we learn from רבי
עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva Well, I'll say in a second. There are a
number of ways you could conceivably get rid of the חמץ. chametz.
I mean you know as a matter of fact what we say
is like you know one of the best ways to have gotten
rid of your חמץ chametz, is to eat it all beforehand, right?
So you could have gotten rid of it by eating it and
that's certainly not a מלאכה. melacha I mean forget about the איסור
issur for a moment about eating חמץ chametz on פסח, but if
we have a מצוה mitzvah of getting rid of חמץ, chametz? what
does that mean? I mean maybe I can just you know throw
it in the ocean, that's getting rid of it. Flush it down
the toilet or eat it or eat it beforehand. That's all legitimate.
You can throw it into the ocean. Why?
You can throw it into
the ocean.
Yeah I know, I understand that. I'm saying but the... But those
are those are all legitimate ways of getting rid of it, but
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying, but we have a problem. We
can't say it means getting rid of it on the first day
because that involves a מלאכה, melacha right? So if I'm throwing it
in the ocean there's no מלאכה melacha there, if I've eaten it,
right,
before, that's there's no מלאכה melacha, involved there.
So it must- it's just in a סוכה, Sukkah, right?
No, I know, no, I'm saying, if I've gotten- no, but it
means if I've gotten rid of it by the first day by
eating it, there's no מלאכה melacha there, right? That's what I said.
It's before, I mean, the סוכה, Sukkah, but in terms of מלאכה,
melacha, there's no מלאכה melacha. by eating it, right? So-
I'm sorry?
Maybe you could sell
it to a non-Jew?
Later in the מסכת. Masechet. That's
well beyond where we are in this דף. But no, I know.
So it must mean if he's saying it involves a מלאכה, melacha.
then it must mean שריפה, sreifah, which is what we do, right?
Even for those even for the position that saying that one of
the best ways of getting rid of חמץ chametz. is by eating
it, you know, we still say that it's good to have a
little bit over to מקיים mikayem the מצוה mitzvah of שריפה. sreifah.
So okay, that's one thing you learn, and שמע מינה הבערה לחלק
יצאה. shma mina havara l'chalek yatza. So now it must mean also
that שריפה sreifah is is an actual מלאכה. melacha, So burning is
an actual מלאכה. melacha Of course burning is a מלאכה, melacha. but
and so fast you may remember from שבת, Shabbat, we have לא
תבערו אש בכל משבתיכם ביום השבת, lo tivaru eish b'chol moshvoteichem b'yom
hashabat, right?
That פסוק. pasuk,
We can't kindle a fire, you can't have,
you know, in your dwelling places on שבת. Shabbat. And then the
question is, well what do we need that for? We all know
that you can't do מלאכה melacha, on שבת, Shabbat. right? There are
other- there are plenty of פסוקים pesukim that
לא תעשה כל מלאכה, lo ta'aseh kol melacha, right, on שבת. Shabbat.
That's what the עשרת הדברות Aseret Hadibrot says you can't do a
מלאכה. melacha. So why do we need to tell you לא תבערו
אש בכל משבתיכם? lo tivaru eish b'chol moshvoteichem?
So that led to the very famous debate
of what הבערה havara is vis-a-vis שבת. Is it just another מלאכה,
melacha right, just like I can't cut down trees, I can't make
a tent, you know, I can't shear, I can't זורע, zoreia, I
can't do
all the other 39- all the 39 מלאכות, melachot, is this one
of them, right? It's another מלאכה. melacha, And what we mean by
לחלק יצאה l'chalek yatza means that
we were trying to say you have a distinct number of מלאכות,
melachot, which means that let's say, you know, I did one and
I got warned and I did the other and I got warned,
right, then I'm liable for like 39 punishments as opposed to if
I did all- as opposed to like doing 39, being חייב chayav
just once. So we get the concept, remember that? We get the
concept of 39 distinct מלאכות, melachot, you know, for 39 איסורים. issurim.
That's what we mean by לחלק. l'chalek. Or it's one of the
39. But the other position was לאו יצאה. lav yatza. No, actually,
since I didn't really need you to tell me anything about הבערה
havara if you're going to say it's a מלאכה melacha. because you
have other פסוקים, pesukim, plenty of other פסוקים pesukim to tell you
that you're not allowed to do מלאכות, melachot, so הבערה havara is
not a מלאכה, melacha. it's rather a לאו, lav, right? So if
I do it, then maybe, you know, then it's-
it's not
איסור מלאכה issur melacha for כרת kareth purposes, it's just a לאו,
lav, right? Just like we have other לאו, lavs, לא ת-, lo
t-, you know, like you can't wear כלאים. kilayim. So same thing,
you can't do this on שבת.
So since רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is telling you though that this
is one of the מלאכות melachot that you can't do, right, and
and he holds ביעור שריפה, biur sreifah, then he must hold that
שריפה sreifah is also a מלאכה. That's basically what we're seeing, that's
what לחלק יצאה, l'chalek yatza, that it's its own separate מלאכה. And
also ושמע מינה לא אמרינן הואיל והותרה הבערה לצורך הותרה נמי שלא
לצורך. v'shma mina lo amrinan ho'il v'hutchra havara l'tzorech hutchra nami shelo
l'tzorech.
We have that principle that on יום טוב Yom Tov once we
say you're allowed to burn it לצורך l'tzorech
אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, that's what לצורך l'tzorech means, I'm allowed to
cook my יום טוב Yom Tov. meal on יום טוב. Yom Tov
So we don't- and we do generally say that all right, well
now that I'm allowed to cook my יום טוב Yom Tov meal,
you know, I can use the hot water for something else, I
can use it to, you know, take a shower for instance, right?
So but we're not saying that for חמץ, chametz, burning חמץ. chametz,
Let's say you have your fire, you know, on burning there to
cook your יום טוב Yom Tov, meal on the first day of
פסח, we don't say all right, now use it to burn the
חמץ. chametz
Because what we're basically- if what he's saying is the principle is
it's something that will benefit you whereas burning the חמץ chametz. is
not benefiting you, it's just getting rid of something, what benefit are
you getting from there, right? You're not- you're not getting a tangible
benefit from it. So
that's what he's saying. So basically you learn those three things. So
since- so since you can't do any of that on יום טוב,
we got to be doing it before, that's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva,
position. So it must-
so you must- it must mean that you've gotten rid of it
before. Again though, even according to רבי עקיבא, how do you know
what it means מדי, midei, you know, it still seems to me
that at some point you're going to- you're going to, you know,
need to use some other לימוד. limud.
Anyways, so there are many the-
the gist of it was there are many ways of of figuring
out. How
we
know that you're getting rid of חמץ chametz not on the first
day of פסח, but you've gotten rid of it
before. Again, one of the more convincing ones, at least to me,
was the היקש. You know you can't have it and and also
that you can't לשחוט את החמץ lishchot et hachametz and then
you
take the various לימודים limudim from there. All right. תנו רבנן שבעת
ימים שאור לא ימצא בבתיכם.
Tanu Rabbanan shiv'at yamim se'or lo
yimatzei bevateichem. So
getting back to our פרשיות parshiyot in בא, Bo,
we have a number of פסוקים pesukim over here.
שבעת ימים מצות תאכלו. Shiv'at yamim matzot tocheilu.
And then אך ביום הראשון תשביתו שאור se'or. מבתיכם. Eat מצות matzot
seven days and the first day you've gotten rid of your שאור.
se'or.
And then just going on a little bit further,
we have that בראשון בארבעה עשר יום לחודש בערב תאכלו מצות עד
יום האחד ועשרים לחודש בערב.
barishon be'arba'ah asar yom lachodesh ba'erev tocheilu matzot ad yom
ha'echad ve'esrim lachodesh ba'erev. שבעת ימים שאור
לא ימצא בבתיכם. Shiv'at yamim se'or lo yimatzei bevateichem. Seven days you
can't have the שאור. se'or
Okay. So
we have שבעת ימים שאור לא ימצא בבתיכם shiv'at yamim se'or lo
yimatzei bevateichem and then we also have what I just mentioned לא
יראה לך חמץ ולא יראה לך שאור בכל
גבולך.
lo yeira'eh lecha chametz velo yeira'eh lecha se'or
bechol gevulecha. So what do we need all that for? Right? Basically
why do we have so many
different פסוקים pesukim saying the same thing?
Good question.
So let me just get a little bit to the end over
here. Here. We have שבעת ימים
תאכל מצות וביום השביעי חג לה'.
shiv'at yamim tocheil matzot
uvayom hashevi'i chag l'Hashem. This is when משה Moshe is saying it
again to בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. מצות יאכל את שבעת הימים ולא
יראה לך חמץ ולא יראה לך שאור בכל גבולך. matzot ye'achel et
shiv'at hayamim velo yeira'eh lecha chametz velo yeira'eh lecha se'or bechol gevulecha.
That's what we're referring to. You have to eat מצות matzot for
seven days and you cannot have חמץ לא יראה לך חמץ. lo
yeira'eh lecha chametz. You cannot have חמץ seen. Now I'm in י"ג
Yud-Gimmel פסוק
ז'.
Pasuk
Zayin. לא יראה לך שאור בכל גבולך. lo yeira'eh lecha se'or bechol
gevulecha. That so that's what we're saying. So I sort of
I'm doing what the גמרא Gemara is doing and I sort of
conflated them as if it's all one time. But really the difference
is
one is when השם Hashem is telling
משה Moshe and the other is when משה Moshe is telling בני
ישראל. Yisrael So it's not really the same thing. If it's all
in the same section that משה Moshe is being told by השם
Hashem then you can say what do we need all the פסוקים
pesukim for? But one is משה Moshe receiving the instruction and the
next one is משה Moshe transmitting the instruction, right? That's really the
פשט pshat of it.
But then maybe the גמרא Gemara would have said, I mean I'm
sort of anticipating the גמרא Gemara could have said is, you know,
ויעש כן, vaya'as kein, משה Moshe could have just said that, you
know? So God said command them and then משה Moshe commanded it.
ויאמר משה אל כל עדת בני ישראל אשר צוה ה' אתו, Vayomer
Moshe el kol adat Bnei Yisrael asher tziva Hashem oto, something like
that, right? Then משה Moshe told the people of ישראל just like
God commanded him. But it doesn't, it goes through it all, what
he told them in very specific details, which is exactly what God
told him. But then the answer to that would be that really
משה Moshe added a whole bunch of other things that God didn't
tell him. He added in תפילין, Tefillin, he added in, you know,
remember this day that took you out of מצרים, Mitzrayim, he added
in a whole bunch of things, right? So that's why you have
to say it there again. It's not really the same and משה
Moshe didn't say exactly what השם Hashem told him,
he added in a whole bunch of different things.
So that's really the answer. But the גמרא Gemara sort of oftentimes
does this that just because, you know, like oh why do we
need to say
this? In שמות Shemot we have this פסוק again in דברים. Devarim.
Obviously for different times, one is it happening, the other is משה
Moshe recounting. But the point being though that the גמרא Gemara always
sort of puts it on one
level field and saying that if we have it in one place
you don't need it in another.
So that's essentially what we're doing over here. So why do we
need these פסוקים pesukim of שבעת ימים שאור לא ימצא בבתיכם shiv'at
yamim se'or lo yimatzei bevateichem if we're going to have it already
לא יראה לך חמץ ולא יראה לך שאור? lo yeira'eh lecha chametz
velo yeira'eh lecha se'or? Right? They kind of
got
the order quoted in גמרא is a little bit different than it's
actually in the פסוק, so you really need to mend it, but
anyway we see the point.
So basically the point is what is one teaching you that the
other isn't? כדשנאמר kedi she-ne'emar לא יראה לך שאור, lo yeira'eh lecha
se'or, this is going to get into our famous דרש. drash. שלך
אי אתה רואה אבל אתה רואה של אחרים ושל גבוה. Shelcha i
atta ro'eh aval atta ro'eh shel acheirim veshel gavo'ah. It says my
שאור se'or, can't be seen. As opposed to saying it can't be
seen in my possession, it doesn't say. It says לא יראה לך
שאור. lo yeira'eh lecha se'or. My שאור, se'or. right, cannot be seen
to you שאור. se'or
But we're saying it means yours. שלך אי אתה רואה. Shelcha i
atta ro'eh. לך Lecha means שלך. shelcha.
I can't, mine can't be seen אבל אתה רואה של אחרים. aval
atta ro'eh shel acheirim. Others can be seen ושל גבוה. ve'shel gavo'ah.
Others, like let's say
a non-Jew or
God's חמץ. That's okay, if it's like הקדש hekdesh חמץ, that's fine.
יכול יהא ב... yachol yehe b...
okay, it can't be seen? All right, fine. I won't let it
be seen. I'll cover it up, right? I'll dig a hole in
my backyard. I'll bury it. So maybe I can do that בפיקדונות
מן הנוכרי, b'pikadonot min hanachri, or I can be מקבל פיקדון mekabel
pikadon from somebody else like a פיקדון. pikadon. Let's say my next-door
neighbor who is not Jewish comes and says, "Here, please, I'm depositing
this חמץ as a
פיקדון. pikadon. My famous cake. Can you keep that for me over
פסח?" תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar לא ימצא. lo yimatze.
No, I can't. And we're going to say what do you mean
you can't? I thought if it's not yours you can. So אין
לי אלא בנוכרי שלא כבשתהו. ein li ela b'nachri shelo k'vashatuhu. And
now we're going to get a very strange teaching. אין לי אלא
בנוכרי שלא כבשתהו. ein li ela b'nachri shelo k'vashatuhu. That might be
only meaning ושרוי עמך בחצר. vesharui imcha b'chatzer. This is only by
a נוכרי nachri that's not under your control, like as in לכבוש.
lichbosh. He's not under your control. He's not like let's say your
slave or something. ואינו שרוי עמך בחצר. ve'eino sharui imcha b'chatzer. He's
not living with you. נוכרי שכבשתהו ושרוי עמך בחצר nachri shek'vashatuhu vesharui
imcha b'chatzer מניין? minayin? How do we know that even a נוכרי
nachri who is under your hand and is living with you can't
even have his חמץ? And then the question is what do you
mean? It should be the opposite, right? It's more of a חידוש
chiddush to tell you
that it's a נוכרי nachri that's not with you that you can
have his חמץ. We're saying it the other way around, right?
So we're going to get to that later. If you didn't get
it this time, we'll get to it later. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar,
לא
ימצא בבתיכם. lo yimatze b'vateichem.
That's why we have that first part שבעת ימים שאור לא ימצא
בבתיכם, shiv'at yamim se'or lo yimatze b'vateichem, right?
Because if it's just יראה yeira'eh then hide it. But no, לא
ימצא lo yimatze means it can't even
be in my possession at all, even if it's hidden. So that's
why we have those first פסוקים. psukim. Okay, אין לי אלא שבבתיכם.
ein li ela sheb'vateichem. It says לא ימצא בבתיכם. lo yimatze b'vateichem.
Okay,
but what if it's בבורות בשיחין ובמערות? biborot bishichin uv'mearot? It's not
in my house, it's in my field. מניין? minayin? תלמוד לומר, Talmud
lomar
that's the other one: לא יראה לך חמץ ולא יראה לך שאור
בכל גבולך. lo yeira'eh lecha chametz velo yeira'eh lecha se'or bechol gvulecha.
Anywhere in your property, not just in my house. That's why we
need both sets of פסוקים psukim because what's in one is not
in the other. ועדיין אני אומר ve'adayin ani omer בבתי b'vati עובר
משום בל יראה ובל ימצא ובטמון ובקבלת פיקדונות מן הנוכרי. over mishum
bal yeira'eh u'val yimatze uv'tamun uv'kaballat pikadonot min hanachri. In the house,
I'm עובר over on all of it from a נוכרי. nachri.
So all those different things. בגבולין, bagvulin, ומה שבגבולין v'ma shebagvulin שלך
אי אתה רואה אבל אתה רואה של אחרים ושל גבוה.
shelcha ee ata ro'eh aval ata ro'eh shel
acheirim veshel gavo'ah. מניין
תתן אמור של זה בזה ושל זה בזה? minayin titen amor shel
ze baze veshel ze baze?
How do we know that it applies in any way, shape or
form? That I can't have my חמץ, another person's חמץ, not in
my house and not in the rest of my property. תלמוד לומר
שאור שאור. se'or se'or. Because we have שבעת ימים שאור לא ימצא
בבתיכם shiv'at yamim se'or lo yimatze b'vateichem
and also it says לא יראה לך חמץ ולא יראה לך שאור
בכל גבולך.
lo yeira'eh lecha chametz velo
yeira'eh lecha se'or bechol gvulecha. So גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. נאמר שאור
בבתים ne'emar se'or b'batim שבעת ימים שאור לא ימצא
בבתיכם shiv'at yamim se'or
lo yimatze b'vateichem ונאמר שאור בגבולין vene'emar se'or bagvulin לא יראה לך
שאור בכל
גבולך. lo yeira'eh lecha
se'or bechol gvulecha. מה שאור האמור בבתים ma se'or ha'amur b'batim עובר
משום בל יראה ובל ימצא ובטמון ובקבלת פיקדונות מן הנוכרי. over mishum
bal yeira'eh u'val yimatze uv'tamun uv'kaballat pikadonot min hanachri.
Just like in one case in your house you can't have it
in any, you can't hide it, you can't receive פיקדונות. pikadonot. אף
שאור האמור בגבולין, af se'or ha'amur bagvulin, so too the שאור se'or
in the larger sphere, in your larger property, עובר משום בל יראה
ובל ימצא ובטמון ובקבלת פיקדונות מן הנוכרי. over mishum bal yeira'eh u'val
yimatze uv'tamun uv'kaballat pikadonot min hanachri. And then similarly מה שאור האמור
בגבולין ma se'or ha'amur bagvulin שלך אי אתה רואה אבל
אתה רואה
של אחרים ושל גבוה.
shelcha ee ata ro'eh aval ata ro'eh shel acheirim
veshel gavo'ah. So too אף שאור האמור בבתים af se'or ha'amur b'batim
שלך אי אתה רואה אבל אתה רואה של אחרים
shelcha ee ata ro'eh aval ata
ro'eh shel acheirim ושל גבוה. ve'shel gavo'ah. So basically what we said
is שאור's se'or in one place and שאור's in the other place
and then but one says in your house and one says גבולין.
gvulin. And just like we דרשנו darshannu in your house is all
these restrictions so too we apply it to גבולין. gvulin. And just
like we learned by גבולין gvulin we apply it to your house.
So basically the point being I can't have my חמץ in my
house or in my גבולין gvulin and it can't be hidden either
in my house or in my גבולין, gvulin, but what you can
have is other people's חמץ. So
now getting back to what we said before: אמר מר amar mar
אין לי אלא בנוכרי שלא כבשתהו ואינו שרוי עמך בחצר.
ein li ela b'nachri shelo k'vashatuhu ve'eino sharui
imcha b'chatzer. This is only, you might have thought that it's only
a problem
with
חמץ from a non-Jew that you're completely dissociated with. He's not under
your thumb so to speak and he's not living with you. כבשתהו
k'vashatuhu as in כבושה. kvusha. Like he's not under your control,
like a
minority population in the state of Israel, essentially.
Basically.
And not living with you. נוכרי שכבשתהו ושרוי עמך בחצר. nachri shek'vashatuhu
vesharui imcha b'chatzer. How do you know that this even applies to
somebody who who is under your control and is living with you?
תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, ועמך *v'imcha*. כפליה *kiflei-ah*, what do you mean?
What direction does this go into? Meaning it's much more of a
חידוש *chiddush* to tell you that it applies even to a חמץ
*chametz* of a נוכרי *nochri* that's not under your control. But we
said that we started by that. The way the גמרא *Gemara* set
it up, it's a bigger חידוש *chiddush* to tell you that you
can't have the חמץ *chametz* of a נוכרי *nochri* that is under
your control. What do you mean? It's a bigger חידוש *chiddush* to
tell you you can't have the חמץ *chametz* of a נוכרי *nochri*
that's not under your control. Right. So, so אמר אביי איפכא *Amar
Abaye ipecha*, all right, switch it. Really, you know, רבא אמר לא
תיפכא *Rava amar lo teipecha*, ורישא קאי *v'reisha ka'ei*. No, it's not
going, it's no no, don't change it, and it's going on the
רישא *reisha*. What do we mean by that? שלך אי אתה רואה
אבל אתה רואה של אחרים ושל גבוה *Shelcha ee atah ro'eh aval
atah ro'eh shel acheirim v'shel gavo'ah*. So we learned that you can't
see your own חמץ *chametz*, but you can see those of others.
אי אלא בנכרי שלא כבוש ואין עמך בחצר *Ee ela b'nochri she'lo
kavush v'ein imcha b'chatzeir*, I understand fine, I can, you know, let
I can see other people's חמץ *chametz*, let's say it's a נוכרי
*nochri* that, you know, that you know that is not under my
control and doesn't live with me. Then it's a then of course
then then you know then it makes then the the bigger חידוש
*chiddush* is saying that I can't see the חמץ *chametz* of someone
that is under my control. It's not going on it's not going
on פקדונות *pikdonos* but it's it's as much like it's going on
saying that of you know yes this I understand then I can
be accepting חמץ *chametz* from a נוכרי *nochri* that doesn't live with
me and is not under my control. How do I how do
I know even that it applies to a נוכרי שכבוש ויושב עמך
בחצר מנין *nochri she'kavush v'yoshev imcha b'chatzeir minayin*, תלמוד לומר לא ימצא
*Talmud lomar lo yimatzei*. So since it says לא ימצא *lo yimatzei*,
then that's coming to teach me that that it's even for a
נוכרי *nochri* that lives with me. What do you mean? והאי תנא
מהדר אהיתירא ונסב ליה קרא לאיסורא *V'hai tanna mahader a-heteira v'nasiv lei
kra l'issura*? The קרא *kra* is saying לא ימצא *lo yimatzei*, what
you can't do, and this תנא *tanna* is trying to tell you
that it means that you can have חמץ *chametz* from a נוכרי
*nochri* that's under your control. How's that possible? ששנה לומר שלך שלך
תרי זימני *She'shana lomar shelcha shelcha trei zimnei*. Because it says שלך
*shelcha* two times. That what do we and
where are the two times that it says it?
That's getting back to our פסוק *pasuk* in דברים *Devarim* that לא
יראה לך חמץ ולא יראה לך שאור בכל גבוליך *lo yeira'eh l'cha
chametz v'lo yeira'eh l'cha se'or b'chol gvulecha* in שמות *Shemos*. Also it
says ולא יראה לך שאור בכל גבולך שבעת ימים *v'lo yeira'eh l'cha
se'or b'chol gvulecha shivat yamim* in דברים *Devarim* in פרשת ראה *Parashat
Re'eh*, פרק טז פסוק ד *perek tet-zayin pasuk daled*. So it says
that again ולא יראה לך *v'lo yeira'eh l'cha*. So since we have
שלך שלך *shelcha shelcha*, it's sort of like, you know, if you
will, it's sort of like the teaching אם אינו עניין לריבוי אם
אינו עניין *im eino inyan l'ribui im eino inyan*, you know, it's
like a ריבוי *ribui*. If you have two things, it's like a
ריבוי *ribui*, right? So so too this is coming to teach you
that since it says שלך שלך *shelcha shelcha* two times, it's actually
מרבה *merabeh* something. And what does it מרבה *merabeh*? It מרבה *merabeh*
the חמץ *chametz* of a נוכרי *nochri* that's even under your control.
And that's the bigger חידוש *chiddush*, that even though he's under your
control and living with you, still nevertheless I'm allowed to see I'm
allowed to have his חמץ *chametz* because it's his חמץ *chametz* and
not mine.
Yeah. A question, the גרסה *girsa* of throughout this סוגיא *sugya*, שטינזלץ
*Steinsaltz* changed נוכרי *nochri* to גוי *goy*. Is there any significance to
that?
I
you know I don't know. I don't at this Artscroll has a
revised edition and you the original edition is is גוי *goy*, which
which I agree and I think that you know I wonder if
I wonder you know in this case it wouldn't be a מין
*min* I don't think because you know the מינים *minim* were still
considered to be to be Jewish, right? So probably נוכרי *nochri* is
is נוכרי *nochri* more pejorative than than גוי *goy*? What do you
think rabbi, would you know?
נוכרי *Nochri*,
נוכרי *nochri* I thought referred to Jewish Christians.
Oh yeah?
I thought. Oh. All right. And גויים *goyim* I thought referred to
pagans.
Maybe that's why. I don't know. Okay.
So
maybe the earlier the earlier version would be גויים *goyim*.
I
thought. I'm not sure. I'm not sure. Okay. Either way, it was
the case of a sensor, like what would the language would they
have changed
to גוי *goy*, would that have been less offensive to the church
than the original would have been נוכרי *nochri*, but they but you're
saying שטינזלץ *Steinsaltz* changed it the other way and says he's changed
it to גוי *goy*.
No, but this isn't in the context of being offensive to the
church. I'm not saying like you know this is just in the
context of חמץ *chametz*, in which case
גוי *goy* would be No, what he's saying is, what I'm saying
is that if it would have referred if the people they were
talking about were were Jewish Christians the text would have originally said
נוכרי *nochri*
and later on
the censor they would have changed it
they would have changed
it so as not to incur the
wrath of the Christian
censor in the middle ages, but but he's saying that שטינזלץ *Steinsaltz*
changed it to גוי *goy* which would be the original, so I
don't know. Maybe.
All right, I think we're going to stop here, it's already 8:30.
Let's get down to the two dots.
I got us to the two dots. Which is, yes, I got
up through תרי זיני. Correct. We're going to pick up tomorrow from
אמר מר. amar mar. It'll go quick.
Thanks, יישר כוח. yasher koach. Thank you.